Okay, let's get started. As a recap of
some of the stuff that we've talked
about so far, um we've formulated this
reinforcement learning problem where we
have states and actions. Uh we have some
uh kind of trajectories that we might be
collecting uh which are sequences of
states and actions. We have a reward
function which tells us how good um is a
particular state and action. uh and also
a policy which is usually what we're
trying to learn. Uh and this is
representing uh the behavior that we're
trying to learn. Uh and then the goal of
reinforcement learning which we talked
about uh in the first lecture is to try
to maximize the expected sum of rewards.
So we want to uh produce behavior that
leads to positive outcomes.
And um we can actually mathematically
write this down as an expectation over
the probability distribution over
trajectories. Uh where this probability
distribution is a function of the policy
which is acting in the world, the
environment dynamics which might be
stochastic uh and of course uh the
reward function.
Uh last week on Friday we started
talking about one way to do this which
is if you have expert demonstrations you
can try to imitate the expert uh by
trying to maximize the likelihood of the
actions that that the demonstrator did.
So trying to actually produce a policy
that leads to actions that the expert
would have taken. This is a very simple
and scalable approach. Uh but it cannot
outperform the demonstrator and doesn't
allow improvement through trial and
error.
Uh we also introduced the notion of an
offline algorithm that only uses an
existing data set and no new data from a
learned policy and an online algorithm
that uses new data from the learn
policy. Uh and today we'll be talking
about uh ways in which we can use
reinforcement learning to outperform the
demonstrator to improve from practice
and specifically we'll be starting to
talk about online reinforcement learning
algorithms.
um particular our first online RL
algorithm will be policy gradients. Uh
we'll talk about a couple different
variants of policy gradients and
introduce both kind of the mathematical
derivation for it as well as some of the
intuition behind it. Uh and policy
gradients are the basis for um some
popular reinforcement learning
algorithms including ones that are used
to train legged robots use uh algorithms
that are used to train language models
um and are also uh kind of part of the
default project. We won't get kind of
the complete algorithm that was used to
train these today, but we will uh get
like most of we're like halfway there
basically and and by Friday we'll have
most of the algorithm for it.
Uh yeah, and then the key goals will be
to try to get the intuition behind
policy gradients, how to implement them
and when to use them.
Okay. Um so the outline of an online
reinforcement learning algorithm uh is
going to look um something like this. So
first we need to initialize our policy
in some way. Uh so we like when you
train a neural network you need to
initialize its weights. Um we could
initialize the weights of our policy
randomly. We could also initialize it
with imitation learning. We could also
use heristics. Um it depends on on the
problem setting. And after we've
initialized uh our policy, we'll run our
policy to collect some data. Uh so we
actually try out different things in the
world. Then we'll use that batch of data
to improve the policy.
And then we will repeat that process.
We'll then collect new data with our
updated policy and update um our policy
again using that latest batch of data.
So we're going to attempt the task and
try to get better. So what this might
look like is the first iteration we kind
of attempt um whatever um some kind of
simple 2D navigation task. Uh the reward
for some of them is bad. the reward for
other trajectories is like okay
and then after more iterations of this
uh we might have a policy that's a bit
better that is able to get higher reward
uh but isn't perfect. So sometimes it
gets higher reward sometimes it still
gets low reward
uh then we'll use that to improve the
policy again and after more iterations
uh hopefully we'll get a policy that is
able to succeed.
Um so this is kind of this notion of
online reinforcement learning where
we're collecting data online and
improving using that data.
Uh so we talked about this reinforcement
learning objective. Uh and the say you
have some policy and you want to
actually understand how good that policy
is. Uh to do that we can't just actually
look at the weights of the neural
network. We actually have to run the
policy to understand how good it is. And
so uh what we'll do is um to estimate
this expectation which is a function of
the policy we could actually just run
the policy multiple times observe the
resulting reward
and then compute the average over the
observed reward and that's an estimate
of how good our policy is.
Um so we can then sum over the samples
from our policy.
Now let's start to think about how we
actually like so we have this trial and
error process. We collect some data and
we improve our policy. Um collecting the
data is is straightforward. We've talked
about how to run a policy to get a roll
out in the environment. We can kind of
sample an action, observe the next
state, then uh run that through our
policy again to get a new action and
repeat that process. Uh but how do you
actually then improve our policy after
we've collected that data?
So we have our objective uh and this can
be written down as we have some policy
pi theta and our goal is to maximize
uh the expected rewards when we sample
from that policy. So uh we can consider
the trajectories that are sampled from
the policy as being drawn by some
distribution that I'll write as p theta
of toao um theta because the
distribution over trajectories is a
function of the policy that you're using
and our goal is to maximize the sum of
rewards. Um, I'm going to use shorthand
here. Uh, and I'm going to use shorthand
for r of the trajectory. Um, where this
just means are like the sum of the
rewards along that trajectory.
Um, so our goal is to maximize uh the
rewards. Uh we're going to maximize this
with respect to our policy parameters
theta.
Now um how do we actually optimize this?
So if we want to use gradient descent
because we typically train neural
networks with gradient descent, we need
to figure out the gradient of this
objective with regard to theta.
And um we'll refer to this
uh
term right here as j theta uh to be able
to to write it. This is the objective
that we're trying to maximize.
And it's a little bit challenging to try
to get a gradient of this thing uh
directly because the relationship uh
that this has on theta is through the
trajectories that we sampled. Uh so we
can't just like differentiate through
this sampling process and that sampling
process also depends on the dynamics of
the world which you also don't know.
Um so if we're going to think about
trying to get a gradient of um
of j theta
um it's helpful to write down this
expectation
um as an integral.
So uh this expectation can be written
as an integral of p theta of toao time r
of toao d to so this is just from the
definition of an expectation.
Um now because
an integral is a summation and that's
kind of a linear operation, we can bring
the gradient um inside the integral. And
so in particular, what that looks like
is the integral of
uh the gradient of p theta of toao
r of tow.
Now, this doesn't really help us um
directly in any way because we don't
want to have to evaluate this integral
in order to take a gradient. Um and at
this point, there is kind of a trick um
a convenient trick uh that we can use to
try to put this into a form that's more
useful.
uh and in particular
the trick is that we'll write it over
here
is that if you think about um
p theta of toao uh times the gradient of
uh p theta of toao actually sorry times
the gradient of the log
Does anyone remember what the gradient
of a log is or the derivative of log
one over? Right? So um then what this is
equal to is this is equal to
p theta of tow*
1 /
p theta of tow. And then we need to use
the chain rule to apply the gradient to
this. And so with the chain rule we'll
get the gradient of p theta of toao.
And these two will then cancel out. And
this is equal to the gradient of p theta
of. And the reason why this is a
convenient equality between gradient of
p theta and this is we could actually
then replace uh the gradient of p theta
down here with this first thing right
here. If we replace this gradient of P
theta oft to right here,
we replace this,
we now get an integral of P theta of
toao time grad
log
P theta of toa
uh time r of toao
p tow.
Um now this is something that's useful
because we can now represent this as an
expectation this this first term right
here. And so this is equal to uh an
expectation of toao sampled from p theta
of toao of grad log
p theta of toao time
r of.
So what we did there is we use this log
trick to then get the P theta out here
and then get an expectation and we're
starting to get to something that's
actually more like what we can evaluate
and in particular this expectation is
something that we can estimate with
samples and now theta is actually
appearing on the inside here. uh and
that means that this kind of uh this is
actually getting closer to something
that we can evaluate if we're still have
this term right here which is doesn't
look like pi of a given s. Um so this is
not this we need to kind of work on this
term but we're starting to get towards
something that we can evaluate. Yeah. So
the question is how is this u more
useful than the first term because we
still have the sampling and uh we need
to the issue with the first case was
that we can't differentiate through the
sampling. Um now the thing that's
different here is that theta actually
appears inside the expectation. Now
we're not going to be able to
differentiate through the sampling
still. Um but the the thing that's
useful here is that we will actually um
be able to differentiate with respect to
theta. Uh, and we're still not going to
differentiate in this part. Um, but
we'll be able to get an estimate um
that's still useful and we could
potentially draw many many samples uh
and then measure this quantity to get
actually a pretty accurate
representation of um of the gradient in
a way that actually depends on theta.
Okay, let's talk a little bit about this
term right here.
So, and actually maybe in case it's
useful in terms of where we're at right
so far, we can show that on the slides
as well. So, um we looked at this J of
theta um wrote it down as an integral.
We found this convenient identity over
here um where P grad log P is equal to
grad P. And then we can use that to
derive this second equation right here.
Um
and now we're right here.
Um so for this part um for grad log p
this is something that we can write out
uh and if we use uh if we remember that
p theta of toao equals p of s1 times
pi of a t given s t and p of s t + 1
given st a t and and
uh with a product over t.
Then when we take the log of this as is
over there, the log
of p theta of toao is equal to the log
of p of s1
plus the
sum over t of the log of pi
plus the log of the dynamics.
And then once we actually take the
gradient of log p to
then the gradient of of this with
respect to theta theta doesn't affect
the initial state distribution. It also
doesn't affect the dynamics in any way.
And so
the gradient of log
p theta of town is equal to just the
gradient of this term right here. So
the gradient of
um
log
pi theta of a given s.
And so this is really useful because
this means that we could actually plug
in um this over there and this is
actually something that we can evaluate.
We can evaluate the gradient of or the
log the gradient of log pi.
Um then this is just taking a backward
path uh through the log of the output of
our neural network.
And so then we actually get a gradient
that we can evaluate. So
um
the gradient that we get when we plug
things in
the gradient of J theta
when we plug this in is we have an
expectation over
trajectory sampled from our policy.
And inside that expectation, we will
have we can bring the gradient inside
that summation. And so we'll have a sum
over time steps of grad
log pi of a t given s
right here. And then we still have our r
of t right here. Um so we can write that
as r of toao. Um we could also write it
as
a summation of r of st comma a t.
So this is the this is what's called the
policy gradient or the vanilla policy
gradient. Uh and
this is a lot nicer than the version up
there because we can sample trajectories
from our policy. Compute their reward.
also compute the gradient of the of each
of of log of pi for each of the actions
and then sum those together multiply and
we can get a gradient that we can apply
to the weights of our neural network
that's actually leading to higher
reward.
So again um on the slides
uh we wrote down what the probability of
a trajectory is. If you take the log of
that, you get um a summation instead of
a product and a log of each of the
individual terms.
Then if we plug that into our gradient
um and we take the
um we take the gradient of log p to then
the first term and the last term go away
because they don't depend on theta.
And then we get uh this final term when
we plug it in.
So this is the gradient. When we do run
policy gradient, we'll collect data and
then we'll evaluate this equation and
then we'll use that uh to represent the
gradient of the the weights of the
policy and then run gradient descent
apply that to our policy and then repeat
the process.
Um so yeah we also talked about this
verbally but in ter in order to estimate
this gradient here we'll run the policy
to collect some data. We'll then improve
the policy um using that data. In
particular you can think of um this the
first summation as collecting n samples
to for that expectation and ideally n is
larger because the higher n is the
better an estimate you're going to get
of the expectation of the integral.
Um and then once we evaluate this
gradient that we're estimating with
samples, we'll then take a gradient step
on our policy parameters.
And so the full algorithm looks
something like sampling trajectories
from our policy,
evaluating an estimate of the gradient
using those samples
and then
applying that to the weights and then
repeating this process to collect a new
batch of data. recomputing the gradient
uh and improving the policy. Um so the
question is what does it look like to
use the data to estimate um this kind of
gradient term right like this first term
or the second term both the first term
yeah so when we're using the data to
compute this first term the um
what we're doing is we're getting a
bunch of states and actions a bunch of
trajectories we're getting n
trajectories that each in this case have
length t time steps and we'll be taking
the states and actions in those
trajectories passing the state through
the policy um as a forward pass to get
the probability over actions. We'll then
evaluate the action in the data um the
probability of that of that action in
the data under the distribution that the
policy output. So if it's like a a
categorical distribution, we'll then get
the probability. We'll take the log of
that probability and then we take the
gradient right here which will just be a
forward pass through sorry a backward
pass through the network. um after
taking the log of the policy output for
that action. Um so this is called the
reinforce algorithm or the vanilla
policy gradient algorithm.
Yeah. So this came out this is just r of
toao. Um so I'm using r of toao as
shorthand for this uh just because I
didn't want to write the summation uh
five times. Uh but yeah this is this is
exactly r of yeah exactly. So this is an
estimate because we're only going to be
taking n samples to estimate this
expectation. If you took infinite then
this would be um this would be exact. Uh
of course taking infinite samples is not
possible. Yeah. So the gradient right
here this is going to depend on the
architecture. Um the question was do we
compute this by hand? Uh you can use um
automatic differentiation. So like
whatever library pietorch or whatever
that can compute that for you. So you
don't have to yeah write it out. Great.
Great. So let's talk about some of the
intuition behind this. So there's the
math. Um but what does this gradient
actually mean? Um so if we look at this
um this maybe let's start by looking at
the first term. Uh the first term um if
we kind of think back to imitation
learning uh this first term is actually
the same as the gradient of the
imitation learning objective. So in
imitation learning we are trying to
mimic actions from some demonstration
data set uh by maximizing the log
probability or minimizing the negative
log probability. Um and if you take the
gradient of that it's uh similarly going
to be um the gradient of the log
probability. So you can think about this
first term as saying I'm going to uh
basically try to increase the likelihood
of the actions in the online data. Um
but then for the second term it's
weighting that by the reward of that
trajectory like how good was that
trajectory.
Um and so you can kind of think about
this as as the imitation gradient but
weighted by the sum of rewards seen in
the data.
And so essentially you're going to
increase the likelihood of actions that
had high reward and decre decrease the
likelihood of actions that were taken in
negative reward trajectories. Uh, and so
you're actually going to be imitating
your own data, the data that was
collected by the policy. Um, but
depending on whether it's high reward or
low reward, you will be um you you
actually might actually be uh have a
negative gradient. If it's negative
reward, that's actually going to push
you away from the bad stuff and push you
towards the good stuff. Yes. Yeah. So,
this is inside the the first summation.
You can see the I comes up right here.
Um, so we're summing a bunch of
directories and then Yeah. This is this
is all within the summation overn. So
the question is is the difference
between this and imitation learning
whereas like imitation learning you're
like kind of either right or wrong or
here you're like this amount of right or
this amount of wrong. Um
so you can apply this well in principle
you can apply this in in scenarios where
the reward is very sparse. Um and so you
can actually apply it in scenarios where
the reward is just like one if you
succeeded and zero otherwise. Um now
this algorithm may not do very well in
those scenarios and we'll talk about
that. Um, one of the key differences
with imitation learning is that you're
actually doing this on your own rollouts
because so you actually the policy is
collecting its own data and then doing
this applying this objective to its own
data. Um, and so that's that's one of
the differences and then second is we're
actually using this reward um whereas in
imitation learning you're just blindly
imitating all the data um without any
notion of how good the data is and it
kind of assumes that it's good data.
Yeah. How do you sample the first state
um of the trajectory? the um this is
something that's typically defined by
the problem setting. So in some problem
settings um like if you're if it's like
you're trying to train um an agent to
play like pinball or something then the
initial state will just be given by the
pinball machine. Um the in other cases
um in like language modeling uh the
initial state or observation might be
the first question that the user asks.
Um so it's kind of usually thought of as
a property of the environment.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So the question is can you
use this to improve imitation learning
um by weighting the trajectories by
reward? Uh yeah you could definitely do
that. Um we will also talk about some of
the good things and bad things about
this objective um in the coming slides.
Yeah. So the question was in practice
does it make sense to start with
imitation learning run that for some
number of iterations and then switch to
this. Um that can definitely make sense.
Uh if you start completely from a
randomly initialized policy it will do
random stuff. Um and if you have a very
dense reward signal that can that can be
okay. Uh but in other scenarios if you
have access to demonstrations then
initializing it with de demonstrations
uh can also can be like a very good fit.
Um and then it will allow you to improve
on top of um your initial policy. Um so
the question is if you don't have a good
conception of like what's good and bad
like what like what the reward function
should be uh can you use imitation
learning to kind of get an initial sense
for that? Um we'll talk about reward
learning in a few lectures um and how
you can potentially use expert data for
that. Um in practice uh it's
challenging. Yeah. Um so we talked about
how this kind of is intuitively
increasing likelihood on high reward
trajectories and decreasing likelihood
on negative reward trajectories. Um if
we actually look at this um visually,
say that we took a few trajectories, one
of them had good reward, one of them had
bad reward, and this red is kind of
showing our initial uh distribution of
trajectories. What this gradient is
going to do is it's going to increase
the likelihood on the green part. So
you'll get something that looks like
this. And then it'll decrease the
likelihood on the red part. So you'll
get something that looks like this. And
it'll encourage the policy um to take
actions that are more like the
highreward trajectory.
Um, in like even more brief terms, you
can think of this as like trying to do
more of the good stuff and less of the
bad stuff that you observe.
Okay? And then you can also think about
this as kind of a formula a
formalization of trial and error where
you're actually um going to try to do
different things and if you see uh good
stuff happening then you'll try to do
more of that and if you make a mistake
then you'll try to stop doing that.
Cool. Um, so now I have a question for
you. So let's look at an example. Say
that we're trying to have a humanoid
learn how to walk in simulation. Uh, and
we'll define the reward function to be
the forward velocity of the robot. This
means that the reward function will be
positive if it's moving forward. It may
also be negative if the robot is moving
backwards. It might be zero if the robot
is not moving.
Um, first we'll sample from our policy.
Say we have a policy that's not very
good at the beginning. Um so in the
first trajectory maybe it falls
backwards. In the second second
trajectory maybe it falls forwards which
will actually technically give it
positive reward. Uh so the sum of
rewards will be positive.
Um maybe in another trajectory it
manages to stand still. So the rewards
would be zero for that. In another
trajectory maybe it takes one small step
forward and then falls backwards. And so
the initial reward um at the beginning
of the trajectory would actually be
getting positive rewards and then later
on it would be getting negative rewards
and the sum of rewards would be
negative.
And then maybe the last trajectory is it
takes one large step backwards and then
a small step forwards and in this case
um it would have kind of negative
rewards and then some positive rewards
but the sum of rewards would still be
negative.
Um now my question for you um is what
will the gradient that we defined here
what will it encourage the policy to do
if this is your data set? If these are
the five trajectories that you um that
you sampled
uh and we'll start we're this is going
to be one of our simpler examples and
then we'll move to more complex examples
in a couple more slides. Um, so I'd
encourage you to pair up for a minute,
discuss it briefly, and then we'll come
back and share in like one or two
minutes. Okay, let's come back. If you
want to share your answer, can you raise
your hand?
Okay, so the gradient will encourage it
to fall forwards and potentially stand
still. So, um, cool. That's mostly
correct. Uh so if we think through each
of these trajectories the first one the
reward uh will be negative here um it
will also be negative this kind of sum
of rewards over the entire trajectory
will be negative for 1 four and five it
should be about zero for three um and
for two it should be the sum should be
positive and so what this means is it
will um you'll get negative gradients
for any actions that were taken in 1
four and five you'll get positive
gradients for all the actions taken in
two and you'll get um roughly zero
gradients for all the actions that are
taken in trajectory 3. And so this means
that it will encourage it to fall
forwards um and it'll encourage it to
not do the things that were in 1, four,
and five. So it will discourage it from
taking steps backwards or forwards and
will also discourage it from falling
backwards. Cool. Um so yeah, so we
encourage it encourage a policy to fall
forwards and not take steps. Uh this is
uh distressing because we don't want our
policy to fall forward. We want it to
take steps. Um and so this is kind of
example of how the polic how the
gradient that we're getting is noisy
high variance. It means that depending
on what these trajectories are, the
gradient might vary drastically. So if
you do actually have some trajectories
that are walking forwards, um you might
actually get a very different gradient
estimate from this set of trajectories.
And so that's kind of the definition of
having noise or having high variance.
Yeah. So the question is why are we
getting multiple trajectories from the
same policy? like why not just get one?
Um there's two reasons for this. One is
that the policy is not deterministic.
And so if we want to explore different
strategies, we will get kind of
different samples of different
strategies because it's
nondeterministic. And the second reason
is also the environment might be
stochastic. And so even if you have a
deterministic policy, you might see
different outcomes and that will this
will help you learn about those
different outcomes. Um yeah, there's one
thing that we can do about this that we
can like already kind of directly
improve the gradient in a fairly simple
way. Um and in particular, um one
observation that we might make is that
if you're in the middle of a trajectory
and you take an action,
um that action has no influence on
previous states.
And right now the gradient that is using
the rewards at all states in the
trajectory to update um in the gradient
update and it's even telling us to take
actions later in the trajectory if your
reward before earlier in the trajectory
was good or bad.
And so one of the things that we can do
is if we one of our trajectories was to
take a large step backwards and then a
small step forwards and we should
actually be able to learn from this
trajectory that taking a small step
forward is is good.
Uh and the way that we can do that is
instead of having this be a sum uh from
t = 1 to t,
what we can instead do is we can
actually have this summation start at t.
Uh and so we can have this essentially
be um let's use a different uh
a different letter. So we'll have t
prime that is starting at t and going to
capital t and now this is uh reward of s
t prime a t prime and by having it only
affect um by having it only look at
future rewards uh this means that we're
now kind of incorporating the fact that
uh current actions can only affect the
future and not affect the past. Oh yes,
sorry. One other thing that you have to
do here. Yes, good point. Is to actually
move this summation um inside this
summation here. Yeah. Why can we do
this? Um so the reason is that we know
that um our action at at a at
let's say um our action at time equals
100. So let's say that like um if t
equals 100. So we're looking at like a
100. um we know that this um 100 is only
going to influence rewards in the future
and the this isn't going to have any
impact on states in the past. So like um
this is going to be completely
independent of like ST50 or sorry S50.
So this doesn't affect like S50 or S51
or S99.
Um and this means that the um yeah
because of that independence we can then
drop the rewards um we can kind of drop
that from the equation and uh
yeah and only look at um when when can
like when looking at like increasing the
likelihood of an action at time t only
use the the future rewards in that
influence.
It's a little bit hard to write out like
mathematically why you can do that. Um,
I can maybe think about whether there's
like a nice mathematical expression for
that. Um, but it's really just about
kind of causality in the world. Um, and
so basically policy behavior at time t
is not going to influence rewards at
earlier time steps. Cool. Um, I think
that this equation, okay, I don't have
the typo in this equation. So yeah,
we're bringing this summation inside the
other one. um and it's only uh going to
be a factor of the future time steps.
And this means that for this example
right here uh we will be um kind of
decreasing the likelihood of actions at
the beginning of the trajectory and then
the future summations will become
positive because you took a step forward
and um then you'll actually start to be
increasing the likelihood of taking a
small step forwards.
Yeah. So, a very good point is it still
doesn't help you if you take a step
forward and then you take a step
backwards. And the reason why um it
doesn't the reason why that's actually a
little bit difficult to handle is that
it's possible that the step forwards
actually cause you to fall backwards or
cause you to take a step backwards. you
don't really know um like a a big part
of reinforcement learning is thinking
about like what influence those actions
have on the future and you need to learn
that from experience and you need to um
if you take a step forwards it means it
it could from the algorithm's point of
view actually have caused something bad
to happen in the future uh and so we
can't uh like drop those uh those
rewards. Um so the question was if you
um say that you had like a lot of really
bad stuff at the beginning and then you
took a good action later on in the
trajectory would you have enough time to
accumulate that? Now um so in your
particular example uh you started
getting um kind of capital t was equal
to 10 and you started seeing um you did
something really good at time step six.
Now um at time step six what this will
look like is you'll have um
grad log um a6 given s6 and then you'll
have a summation from t prime equals 6
to 10 of r s t prime a t prime and so if
you did get a high reward from that
action immediately or in the next four
time steps then you would actually
increase the likelihood on that action.
Now, um it's really going to depend a
lot on the reward function. Um so you're
saying that for short horizon, for kind
of fixed horizon problems, um you're
actually going to be giving it a the
gradient will be different um if you're
summing over 10 rewards or versus over
four rewards. Um so one of the things
that's important if you have a fixed
time horizon t is um for this to be a
proper state and actually to be truly
marovian you need it to contain
information about um like the future
dynamics. And so the um and if it if
it's fixed at 10 and you don't actually
um and the policy doesn't know if the
horizon is about to finish then it's
actually not a truly marovian state and
you need to actually give it information
about how many time steps it has left to
succeed and then you can incorporate
that into the state. Um and so you would
actually have different states in those
different circumstances.
Okay. Um so I have now another example
for you and this actually comes back to
the question that came up earlier. um
although it's actually be slightly
different. So say that the robot um we
now have a version that is only
depending on future rewards. Um we have
the same version of the problem but now
our policy is a little bit better. Um
one of the trajectories falls forward,
one of the trajectories kind of slowly
stumbles forward, one of the
trajectories suddenly walks forward and
one of the trajectories runs forward. Um
my question for you is what will the
gradient encourage the policy to do? um
in this case uh and we can use the um we
can use the the this version the kind of
updated version um yeah and so I'll
encourage you to pair up again and
discuss this and then we'll come back in
like two minutes
okay let's come back
please raise your hand if you want to
share your answer
okay yeah So the the first answer was
that like it's going to get highest
reward for the stuff that is moving
forward at higher velocity. So it's
going to encourage it to do that um the
highest velocity stuff the most. And you
were saying that even if it makes any
sort of forward progress, it'll still
encourage it to do that. Yeah. So
another hypothesis was that if you kind
of go back to the previous example, it
might encourage it to fall forward and
then get back up again and then fall
forward and get back up again,
especially if it's like um easy to fall
forward. Now getting up again is
actually a little bit more challenging.
So that might also be a little tricky.
And so the thoughts there was that the
fourth one if the reward is um it might
dominate if that one has a much higher
reward than the others. If it's um if
they're more kind of even in terms of
velocity and it's just like move forward
then um it won't necessarily dominate
and you'll do all four. Yeah. So all of
the rewards in these cases will all be
positive. Uh and so even so the kind of
I think what a lot of people are getting
at is that the kind of reward of this
last one will be the highest and so it
will be encouraged to do this but
because all of these also like one two
and three also have positive rewards the
policy is actually also still going to
be encouraged to do those things. Um so
because uh basically the with this term
is is is non- negative when it's
positive um you're still going to be
increasing the likelihood on the actions
in these trajectories. Um, now it won't
do it as frequently as running forward,
but it will still be encouraged to do
that. Um, and that might be a little bit
concerning because um, it sometime some
some of the time it will actually be
encouraging it to stumble forward and
ideally we would actually um, in this
case want a policy that can um, actually
have the policy run as fast as possible.
Yeah. Yeah. So the question was is this
because of local minimum like it seems
like with this reward function like it
really the best outcome is to run
forward and so um like why are we
getting this kind of objective? Uh the
reason for this is because the gradient
is noisy. It kind of comes down to
variance and if you do have a policy
that runs forward it will encourage it
to keep on running forward. Um but when
you have other data in there um that
kind of that other data will influence
it in some ways and so it won't
necessarily converge to a local optimum
um because at this point it will
encourage it to run forward more and
then the next batch of data will run
forward more and they'll encourage it to
run forward even more. So eventually it
will converge to the global optimum but
um it will get there more slowly because
the gradient has a lot of variance
depending on the samples that you
select. Will this encourage the robot to
roll forward? Um,
with this data, it will not encourage it
to roll forward unless some weird
combination of gradients causes that.
Um, but yeah, generally it will not. Um,
if you had data of rolling forward, then
it would encourage it to roll forward.
The question is, can the agent learn
from a subset of trajectories instead of
the whole trajectory? Um, in this case,
it will learn from all future steps in
the trajectory. So that is a subset but
it might not be um and I guess in the
next lecture we'll talk about like more
sophisticated ways um to to estimate
this uh that might are are smarter
basically.
Um cool. So the thing that we saw here
is that things are sensitive to the
scaling of the reward function. And on
the flip side if everything was negative
like came up in the question before we
would actually only be getting negative
gradients uh to our policy and not no
actual positive gradients. Um and that's
actually a big problem with um with this
kind of approach is that it's very it
kind of depends on the scale of the
reward. And there's actually a very
simple thing that we can do to fix this.
Uh and so in particular uh what we can
do is when we are using this gradient of
um which is kind of the um expectation
of p of toao of um I'll maybe do the the
kind of the first version just to make
it a bit shorter. Um but we get the
gradient of
uh log p of toao time r of toao. And
what we can do is instead of having this
be r of toao, we could actually subtract
um a constant
uh where that constant
uh could be equal to the average reward.
And if we subtract the average reward
from this, this means that things that
are better than average will get a posit
will get kind of will increase the
likelihood. And things that are below
average will actually lead us to
decrease likelihood. So this will be
negative.
Now uh you might be wondering
can we just add this B here? Uh did I
just like um make that up? Like why why
can we do that? Why are we allowed to do
that? Um
the
we can see what the effect that this has
on the gradient and what we can show is
we can actually show that if you
subtract a constant um in expectation
this has zero effect on the gradient. um
and in particular so this is the
gradient of J
and if we look at what effect this has
on the gradient and expectation
we can look at essentially the
expectation of
um
grad log P time uh time B
And it's possible to show that this uh
in expectation is actually equal to
zero. Uh and in particular
um if we
write this out as the gradient of uh or
sorry the integral right the expectation
is the integral of p of toao um times
grad log p of toao time v
to
the we can then use the same uh kind of
use the same trick that we used before
but in reverse. This is equal to the
integral of
um grad
p theta of toao time b d to
um I'm a little bit out of space but the
gradient can be moved to the outside of
the integral because um because of kind
of this is a linear operation. We can
also move B outside the integral because
it's a constant. And so
this is equal to
um
the
gradient uh B times the gradient of the
integral
of P theta of to D to. Now this integral
is just equal to one and the gradient of
one is zero.
So this is one this uh is zero and b * 0
is zero.
Uh and so this means that the kind of
the x expectation this is going to have
zero effect on the gradient. Um, and so
just to maybe write that out a little
bit more cleanly, um,
the expectation of the gradient of log P
* V. So basically the effect that this
baseline is having on this gradient, we
can write that as the integral. Um, we
can then use the log trick in reverse.
We can move B and the gradient outside
of the integral. Um, this integral is
equal to one. the gradient of one is
zero and then we get zero. So this means
that we can add this baseline. Yeah. So
the reason why this constant term the
question was like um this constant term
wouldn't be helpful if we could actually
truly u evaluate the expectation and
yeah that's correct. So if we had this
expectation and could measure this
exactly that we wouldn't need this. Um
the reason why this is helpful is
because we have this expectation and um
this basically you can think of it as
reducing it's a way to reduce the
variance of your estimate of this
expectation. Um and it's an unbiased way
to do that. Uh so in particular um as
long as the baseline is a constant um
then it won't change the behavior of the
gradient and expectation. This means
that it's unbiased. This is a term from
statistics talking about like um effect
on random variables and you can show
that it reduces the variance of your
estimate of the gradient. Yeah. So the
question is is B really a constant? It
seems to depend on the trajectories. Uh
we'll use the same uh the same value of
B uh for an entire batch for all of the
examples. And so we'll collect a batch
of data then we will compute B and we'll
then use B for all of the updates. um in
uh on that batch of data. Yeah. So how
does it produce the variance of the
gradient? Um you can write down so this
is the kind of the expectation of the
gradient. You can write down the
variance analytically um and show that
it reduces the variance. Um you can kind
um I don't want to go through the math
uh because we have some other stuff to
get through. Um but kind of intuitively
you can think about it in terms of um
this example of um it will like yeah
encourage it to do more of the good
stuff more of the above average stuff
and less of the below average stuff. Um
the I could also mention that average
reward is actually not the optimal
baseline. Uh you can actually derive the
variance um and then uh find like then
take the derivative of the variant set
equal to zero to find the optimal
baseline. Um but average reward is
pretty good. Uh the optimal baseline is
something like um kind of it's very
close to average reward but there's some
additional waiting terms.
Um cool. So we have one more episode of
what does the gradient do? Uh and we're
going to look at a different example.
Um, in this case, uh, the robot is
folding a jacket, and the reward is one
if it's neatly folded, 0.5 if it's
folded with some wrinkles, and zero if
it's not folded. Um, we're going to
again sample from our policy. Uh, we
have some samples of not touching the
jacket, folding only the sleeves, but
not folding the full thing, um,
flattening the jacket but not folding
it, and one trajectory where it does
fold the the jacket. Um and my question
is uh with the baseline in here this
time um what does the gradient look
like? The uh the rewards for 1, two and
three will be zero and the reward for
four will be positive. And so this means
that because of our baseline the
gradient for four will be positive and
we'll encourage this behavior and then
we'll discourage all the behavior for
one, two and three. Now in some ways
this is good uh because it means that we
are encouraging uh the good behavior. Uh
but there are also some things that are
a little bit dissatisfying about this.
Uh the first is that um the gradient for
1, two and three is going to be
identical for all of them. Uh there
isn't any differentiation between them.
Um and some of these are actually better
than others. And this is kind of in some
ways a result of the reward function
that we're using which is more sparse
than it could be. Um and the other thing
is that we'll we'll actually see some
techniques um in Friday's lecture that
would actually um be able to leverage
some of the good parts of these
trajectories because there is a good
thing about folding the sleeves and it
would be nice to be able to use that
data to encourage the policy and right
now it will actually be discouraged um
and have negative gradients for this
trajectory. So in some ways this is
good. Um so it will encourage folding
but the gradient is constant um for
trajectories one, two and three. Uh and
we will um on Friday we'll see ways to
make this a little bit better. Um and
kind of one of the takeaways here is
that policy gradient is still noisy and
is still high variance. Um and it really
is going to work best if you have dense
rewards rather than rewards that are
sparse. And it'll work best if you have
large batches of data because if you
didn't actually sample this fourth
trajectory and you only sampled
failures, uh then you would have zero
gradient and you wouldn't actually be
able to improve. Um so the question was
can we just improve the reward function?
Uh yes. So if we had a more dense reward
function, um that would definitely help
in these cases. Uh there are actually
scenarios still where um where that
could do uh we could do better. So
especially if you for example folded the
sleeves uh got positive reward for this
and then like dropped it on the ground
or something after that then that's
still dissatisfying because we wouldn't
use the first part successfully. Uh and
we'll actually see how to do that how to
get get good gradient for that first
part on Friday. But yeah, if you had a
more dense reward function for this
particular uh set of trajectories that
would uh work a lot better. Oh, so the
question here is when we do the
baseline, are we also using this trick
to only use future rewards? Um, you can
combine them. Uh, it's you need to be a
little bit um you need to think a little
bit potentially more carefully about
what the baseline will be. Um because
some of the rewards um uh you'll be
summing over fewer things or more things
depending on where you are in the
trajectory. Uh but you can definitely
combine them. Yeah. So the question was
for if we're using average reward as the
baseline um do we need to keep updating
the term? Do you need to use data from
the policy? Um, so yes, you'll want to
keep on updating it because as the
policy gets better, um, what's above
above average and below average will
change. Uh, and you'll want to
recomputee it on your latest, uh, batch
of data.
Cool. Um, so one more thing on this
version of the algorithm and then we'll
move on uh to one last version. Um, in
terms of how to implement it, we talked
about we kind of derived a gradient um,
like this. And to actually implement
this in practice, you could uh, in
principle actually just run a backward
pass for all of these different terms.
Um, but if you computed all these
individually, then you'd have to do n* t
backward passes. And this would be
rather inefficient.
Uh, and it'd be nice if we could just
actually do automatic differentiation on
the full objective and only do one
forward pass and one backward pass. Uh,
and we can do that. So, it's possible to
implement essentially a surrogate
objective whose gradient is the same as
this objective. I'm calling a surrogate
because it's not the same as like the
very first objective of maximizing
expected rewards. Um, uh, but you can
write down a surrogate objective for
this particular example. Um, this is
what the surrogate objective looks like.
Note that I actually um do have a typo
on these equations where this second sum
should be inside the first sum. Um,
that's maybe a small note. I'll see if I
can fix that. Um, but uh yeah, you can
implement a surrogate objective and then
use back prop and autodiff software to
um just do one backward pass.
Okay. Um and what this actually looks
like in practice is this would actually
look like a cross entropy loss for a
discrete action policy. Um or something
like squared error for a gausian policy.
Um you could also use more sophisticated
policies um like diffusion or or
something like that as well.
Okay. So summary so far um we showed how
to estimate the gradient of the RL
objective using this log gradient trick.
Um this corresponds to weighing the
policy likelihood by future rewards. And
we found that subtracting a baseline
like average reward um will also further
improve the gradient. Um even with these
two things, the gradient is still noisy
and so it's best with large batches and
dense rewards. Um this is also our first
online reinforcement learning algorithm
where we iterate between collecting a a
batch of data with our policy and
improve our policy and it kind of
formalizes this trial and error uh
learning process.
Um, and the kind of the intuition for
everything we've done so far is do more
of the high reward stuff and less of the
lowreward stuff.
Okay. Um, now the last thing we'll talk
about today is what else is troublesome
about policy gradients. Um, and one
thing that we haven't really talked
about that much is the details of the
sampling process. And this is what our
gradient in our algorithm looks like.
And note that in this gradient, this
assumes that we're sampling from pi
theta. And
we change theta in step three.
And this means that every single time we
take a single gradient step, we need to
recollect data to estimate our gradient.
Um, and this is kind of sad because
usually we do like thousands and
thousands of gradient steps on neural
networks.
Um
and so yeah that seems like a problem.
Um and what this is called is it's
called on policy. It means that the
gradient that we are measuring is like
requires data using our exact policy. Um
and we can think about this as an
attribute of an online orall algorithm
where on policy only uses data from the
current policy and off policy means that
you can reuse data from other past
policies.
Um, so can we derive an off policy
version of the policy gradient? And it's
only going to be a little off policy.
Uh, and by that I mean we're just going
to try to be able to take more than one
gradient step on a single batch of data.
Um, and to do this we can use important
sampling. Um, and important sampling is
actually a really cool technique that's
useful outside of reinforcement learning
as well. uh and it's kind of thinking
about this um this scenario where you
want to estimate a quantity uh an
expectation when you don't actually uh
without actually sampling from that
distribution. So say you have uh some
expectation
uh using samples from p of x and you
want to estimate um some function f ofx
using those samples. But say that you
only have access to the ability to
sample from Q of X. Um, so this is
usually called like your proposal
distribution that's able to kind of
propose uh samples to use. This is like
your old policy. We have samples from
our old policy, but we want to be able
to estimate a function of samples of our
new policy after we've taken a gradient
step.
So what you can do in this case um if
you write down this expectation as an
integral um it looks something like this
and
as long as q of x has uh reasonable
support we can write this as we can kind
of add in this term that equals 1
into
um our equation.
And then we can now actually write this
as an expectation with respect to Q.
So this is equal to
an expectation
with respect to Q of
uh P of X
divided by Q ofX
times F ofX.
And so this means that we can actually
estimate uh we can like get this
expectation
by sampling from Q and then waiting the
quantity by P over Q.
Um so that's pretty cool. Uh this means
that we can use on principal samples
from our old policy
um Q weight them by the probability of
the sample under our new policy divided
by the probability under the old policy
times the quantity.
Um so we showed this for um kind of this
simple case of P of X and Q of X. uh in
terms of actually applying this to
our policy,
we can take our expected rewards with
regard to key of data. If we instead
have some previous policy that we've
collected samples from, we can then
measure our objective in terms of the
samples from that policy where we weight
the reward by the new policy divided by
the old policy probability.
Now note that this requires the um your
proposal distribution to have non-zero
support. Um in scenarios where the um
where your your new policy has
probability. This is actually very
important for it to work. If Q ofX is
zero, this is uh not poorly defined. Um
but that's really the the only catch
here. Um, and in general, this is going
this important sampling technique is
really going to work best when P and Q,
um, or when your old policy and your new
policy are very similar to each other.
Um, now there's some details. We've
shown this in terms of P of TOAO. Now,
how do we actually do this in terms of
pi of A given S? Um, that actually gets
a little bit trickier. Uh, we can write
down P of tow and this ratio uh, as the
product of these different
probabilities.
Um, and fortunately some of the
probabilities cancel out.
But when we then try to put this um put
these probabilities into
um into our update, we're going to get
something like this.
Uh where we then have this product of
these ratios, these probability ratios.
Um, and now unfortunately this product
can actually become very small or very
large if the length of your trajectory
is very large. Um, because you're going
to be multiplying many many numbers
together. Like if you have a 100 numbers
that you're multiplying together, if
they're above one, that might start to
get very large. If they're below one,
that might get to zero very quickly. Uh,
and so in practice, um, we often will
consider the expectations over time
steps instead of trajectories. Uh and
that also has a little bit of a hitch
which is that this needs to be over
state action pairs um rather than
actions given states. Um but we can
often in practice we can approximate
this ratio as equal to one. This is
incorrect but um it's kind of the best
that we can do and then we can get some
final form where we get this ratio of um
new policy over old policy.
Um
cool. Uh
the full algorithm looks the same except
now we can take multiple gradient steps
on the same batch. Um this is good. And
then we have this new uh form for our
gradient.
Okay. Um we'll talk a little bit about
um some tricks. Uh we don't have time to
cover uh kale constraints today. Um but
to review things talked about online
arrowl. It's an on policy algorithm. We
talked about baselines for reducing
variance and we also just derived this
off policy policy gradient which uses
important sampling um and allows us to
apply multiple gradient steps. The
intuition is to do more high reward
stuff and less low reward stuff and the
gradient is still very noisy and best
with batch large batches and dense
rewards. Um cool. Uh and that's it for
today. Next time we'll talk about actor
critic methods which will build closely
on what we talked about today including
PPO.